Bert Whitman Papers
Bert Whitman Papers
1937-1968
1957-1968
Whitman, Bert.
2 linear ft.
200 original editorial cartoons, sketches, correspondence and miscellaneous material.
2651182
Biographical History
Bert Whitman (1908-1990) was an American editorial cartoonist and comics artist.
Bert Whitman was born in Brooklyn on July 27, 1908. A self taught artist, Whitman worked for the Los Angeles Times at age 16. He drew for the Detroit Mirror from 1929 until 1932 and was on the staff of the Cincinnati Enquirer during 1937. Whitman then began working on comic books. From 1939 until 1945, Whitman contributed to projects produced by Fox Comics, Fawcett, DC Marvel and Novelty Comics. He also created Mr. Ex for the Chicago Tribune Comic Book which first appeared in January 1941. It was later moved to the Tribune’s main comics page but was cancelled in the summer of 1943.
Whitman also worked on a variety of syndicated comic strips in the 1940s. Whitman wrote Cynthia and drew Debbie Dean for the New York Post Syndicate from 1942 until 1949. Comics historians have speculated that Debbie Dean ended after Whitman used the word "dope" in one of the strips which the censorship board objected to.
Following his time at the Miami Herald from 1948 to 1952, Whitman began working as an editorial cartoonist for the Stockton Record in Stockton, California where he stayed until moving on to the Phoenix Gazette in 1969.
Whitman was a member of the American Cartoonists Society and was recognized by a variety of organizations. He was a three time winner of the American Cancer Society Award in 1953, 1954, and 1956 and received the Disabled American Veterans Citation in 1958. Whitman won ten straight Freedom Foundation Awards and honored with their Distinguished Service Award. The National Conference of Christians and Jews Award was given to him in 1956 and 1963.
Whitman, also an avid painter, had his works exhibited by the San Francisco Museum of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City and at various smaller galleries. Bert Whitman died of natural causes on December 10, 1990 in Phoenix, Arizona.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bert Whitman Papers are organized into four series: Cartoons, Sketches, Correspondence and Miscellaneous.
There are 200 original, numbered editorial cartoons drawn by Whitman for the Stockton (Calif.) Record during the 1950s and 1960s in the Cartoons series. The cartoons are signed by Whitman, but most of the cartoons are undated, but a few having dates stamped on the back.
Also in the Bert Whitman Papers are 26 rough pencil Sketches with captions.
Correspondence contains approximately 30 pieces of correspondence from readers (1937-1967). Included are both pieces of fan mail and hate mail. Of particular interest is a signed letter from J. Edgar Hoover thanking Whitman for sending him an original cartoon of Hoover that was published in the Cincinnati Enquirer.
Finally, a folder of Miscellaneous contains a photograph of Whitman (1966) and an assessment of the monetary value of 150 of the cartoons (1967) and a brief biography.
Arrangement of the Collection
The Cartoons are arranged by number in order from #1-100 followed by a second set numbered #1-50. The Sketches, Correspondence and Miscellaneous are arranged as received.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Whitman, Bert.; Stockton Record (Stockton, Calif.); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- California.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Peace -- United States.; Political cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Editorial cartoons.; Sketches.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bert Whitman, 1967-1968.
Inventory
- Cartoons, circa 1957-1968; See below for an index to the cartoons.; 200 items 15" x 17 1/4"
  - #1-10, 1. SURE PEPS US UP ANYWAY; 2. THE LADY WITH ENIGMATIC SMILE; 3. THERE'S GOING TO BE MORE CRAZY MIXED-UP RUSSIANS FROM NOW ON; 4. NO IMMEDIATE PLANS FOR REMOVAL; 5. RED CHINESE ROPE TRICK; 6. ONE FOURTH ANGEL-THREE FOURTH'S PEST; 7. TO SWIM OR NOT TO SWIM; 8. COME TO THINK OF IT; 9. THE SHOW'S ON THE ROAD; 10. BIG GUIDEPRINTS (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - #11-20, 11. STILL FAR FROM BEING AN ANGEL!; 12. A FELLOW CAN DREAM, CAN'T HE?; 13. BROWN PITCHING; 14. OTHER MEMORIES; 15. HE MADE PEOPLE LAUGH FAMED COMEDIAN OLIVER HARDY; 16. SOMEWHERE THERE'S AN IDEA HERE; 17. INSIDE DOPE!; 18. HOW MUCH ADHESIVE IS REALLY NECESSARY?; 19. PROGRESS, IT'S WONDERFUL-BUT-; 20. THEY SAY EVERY DOG HAS HIS DAY (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - #21-30, 21. TOP BANANA; 22. ENOUGH TO GIVE A PERSON A COMPLEX; 23. DUSTING OFF AN OLD ONE; 24. THE NEXT SOUND YOU'LL HEAR---; 25. NOBODY HERE BUT US FISH!; 26. THE NAKED TRUTH; 27. WORKING ON IT; 28. WE KNOW WHO WE'RE BETTING ON; 29. NOW, IF ONLY MR. K. HAD A CONSCIENCE, TOO-; 30. CAN'T HELP BUT BE AN IMPROVEMENT (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - #31-40, 31. DEEPER GROW THE ROOTS; 32. THINK OF THE BILLIONS IT WILL COST TO FIND OUT!; 33. STILL DOING BUSINESS ON THE OLD CORNER; 34. IS THIS WHAT YOU'D LIKE?; 35. QUIZ SHOW INVESTIGATIONS; 36. WHAT'S NEW AT THE PENTAGON; 37. THE IRRESISTIBLE MEETS THE IMMOVABLE; 38. WHY NOT? IT'S AS GOOD A REASON AS ANY; 39. YOU AN EARLY BIRD?; 40. COULD BE A BEAUTIFUL ROMANCE (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - #41-50, 41. AN UNFUNNY THING HAPPENED TO ME ON THE WAY TO THE REPUBLIC!; 42. PROMISED LAND; 43. THE OLD PRO; 44. THE DAY THE SAPLING HAD TO CRY; 45. OPERATION: CUSTOMERS; 46. BIG LOAD TO CARRY, POP!; 47. TO YOU FROM ALL OF US; 48. MAKING HIM THINK A WAY OUT; 49. DON'T PUSH TOO HARD; 50. GOLDEN RULE (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - #51-60, 51. THE ICEMAN GOETH? 52. LET IT RAIN!; 53. NEW WORLDS TO CONQUER; 54. THE DECISION; 55. MIXED-UP ABOUT DAYLIGHT SAVINGS END; 56. HEADACHES, ANYONE?; 57. PRINCIPLE INVOLVED; 58. NO NOTICEABLE THAWING AS YET; 59. EUGENEO PACELLI: MAN OF PEACE; 60. KNEE DEEP (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - #61-70, 61. GOOD TRICK IF IT CAN BE DONE; 62. 'A LAMP UNTO MY FEET, AND A LIGHT UNTO MY PATH!'; 63. CAME WITH THE OFFICE EQUIPMENT; 64. NOW WHO WAS IT WHO THOUGHT BATISTA WAS SO BAD??; 65. ALWAYS BE POLITE - EVEN IF YOU DON'T UNDERSTAND; 66. HONK! HONK! HONK! HONK!; 67. THE PICK-ME-UP; 68. PLOP!; 69. THOUGHT IT WASN'T LOADED; 70. THE LONG WAIT (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - #71-80, 71. WHAT NOW, MY MASTER?; 72. SMALL WORLD; 73. FACTS OF LIFE; 74. MAN WANTED; 75. ONLY AT FIRST IT HURTS; 76. THANK HEAVEN FOR LITTLE GIRLS; 77. LIKE TO BE GOVERNOR OF CALIFORNIA; 78. SOME THINGS MAKES THE OLD GIRL FROWN; 79. THE HOT ONE; 80. WON'T BE LONG NOW (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
  - #81-90, 81. 'THE TUMULT AND THE SHOUTING DIES; THE CAPTAINS AND THE KINGS DEPART;' 82. STRANGE LOOKING TUNNEL OF LOVE; 83. IT'S YOUR DIAL-TURN IT; 84. OLD FASHIONED TROUBLESHOOTER; 85. NOMINATION FOR THE MEANEST-THING-EVER-CLUB; 86. SOMEBODY'S GOT SOME DIRTY WASH; 87. NEEDED: ANOTHER HOUDINI; 88. STRANGE WHAT SEEMS IMPORTANT TO SOME; 89. DRY SPELL COMING UP; 90. MACK THE KNIFE (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
  - #91-100, 91. THERE GO THE HORNS AGAIN; 92. HAVE WE FOUND THE ABOMINABLE SNOW MAN?; 93. 'BE IT EVER SO HUMBLE-'; 94. "HAPPY ;ITTLE-OVER-A-YEAR-OLD REGIME, DEAR CASTRO, HAPPY- ETC., ETC, ETC.; 95. WORLD OF TOMORROW?; 96. WOW!! WHAT AM I WAITING FOR?; 97. 'ON THE FIRST DAY OF SPRING MY TRUE LOVE GAVE TO ME---"; 98. THAT 'NOT WANTED' FEELING; 99. BUSY DAYS, WEATHERWISE; 100. AT LAST: CLOSE HARMONY (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
  - #101-110, 101. SIMPLE SIMON META PIEMAN; 102. AND IT'S FIRST HAND; 103. PAY AS YOU RIDE? WOW!; 104. GOOD NIGHT SWEET PRINCE; 105. AND THE RACE GOES ON; 106. CALMED LITTLE HELLION; 107. OLD STUFF; 108. NO DISCORD ON THIS; 109. WE'RE LEANING OVER BACKWARD; 110. AND SOME BRAILLE (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - #111-120, 111. PEPS UP WHAT MIGHT HAVE BEEN THE SAME OLD EASTER BONNET; 112. HOPE NIKITA ISN'T OVERLY SENSITIVE; 113. SUPPOSE THIS HAPPENED?; 114. AMERICANS - ENGLISHMEN, HAVE ALWAYS SPOKEN THE SAME LANGUAGE BASICALLY; 115. HO HUM!; 116. MOMMY'S DAY; 117. RINGSIDE SEAT-BIG SKY; 118. THE UGLY AMERICAN; 119. NEVER A DULL MOMENT; 120. LAME DUCK? (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - #121-130, 121. CHECK IN; 122. YOU'VE MET PALOOKAS BEFORE, JOHN - JUST KEEP PUNCHING - PUNCHING, AND WE'RE IN; 123. HOT STUFF; 124. WHEREVER HE IS, THE OLD BOY MUST BE HAPPY ABOUT THE NEWS; 125. NEEDED: DEMONSTRATORS AGAINST THE DEMONSTRATORS; 126. IS THAT WHAT'S NEW PUSSYCAT; 127. FORMOSA CALLING; 128. OLD FAITHFUL; 129. HELPING HAND?; 130. HASN'T FOOLED ANYONE EXCEPT HIMSELF (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - #131-140, 131. GIFT OF MAGIC; 132. "TESTING-1-9-5-6TESTING-"; 133. WE KNOW YOU'VE GOT ONE-JUST OPEN IT UP!; 134. TEN YEAR OLD ASKS FOR SIMPLE EXPLANATION OF THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN A REPUBLICAN AND A DEMOCRAT; 135. JUST PLAIN FOLKS; 136. THE MORAL ESCAPES US; 137. KICK THIS AROUND FOR A WHILE; 138. LESSON AT MELBOURNE; 139. THE LAST WORD; 140. MOST BEAUTIFUL AMERICAN WORD IN THE WORLD (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - #141-150, 141. 'I'M ALL RIGHT - EVERYBODY ELSE IS CRAZY'; 142. -LIVED THE LIFE HE LOVED- LOVED THE LIFE HE LIVED; 143. JOS. R. McCARTHY 1909-1957; 144. CHRISTMASVIEW OF THE MIDDLE EAST; 145. AVOID THIS EPITAPH; 146. LOST HORIZON; 147. THE PRESIDENT IS IN CONFERENCE; 148. 'I WANT A PIECE OF YOUR BANANA CREAM PIE, MOM!'; 149. THE 'DO-IT-YOURSELF' ERA; 150. THERE'D BE A RENDEZVOUS! (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
  - #1-12 (set 2), 1967-1968; 1. WELL AND GOOD, BUT IS IT STEADY WORK?; 2. SPECIAL AWARD; 3. HOW THE LONG HAIR SET IS COGITATING; 4. SOMETHING BREWING, LYNDON?; 5. MODERN TIMES; 6. NOISY DAYS ON PENNSYLVANIA AVENUE; 7. ANOTHER DAY - ANOTHER HEADACHE; 8. MARCH WINDS - NEW HAMPSHIRE; 9. WILL - 0 - THE - WISP; 10. 'YOUR VOICE TELLS ME, 'NO, NO', BUT THERE'S -, -!, IN YOUR EYES!; 11. "WOW! WOTTA COMEBACK!"; 12. JAVELIN THROW (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
  - #13-19 (set 2), 1967-1968; 13. 'A FOND MEMORY, SON!"; 14. NONE SO DEAF AS THOSE WHO WILL NOT HEAR; 15. JUST 'BE COOL' THEY SAY! 'BE COOL', BE COOL', BE COOL!'; 16. THE EXPERTS; 17. THE WATCH; 18. AT LAST! SOMETHING REALLY WORTH PROTESTING; 19. 'HAPPY ANNIVERSARY, AMIGO!' (Oversize 2, Folder 7)
  - #20-34 (set 2), 1967-1968; 20. UNSUNG HERO 1967; 21. NOSTALGIA; 22. "I'M NOT SO CERTAIN BEING AN ADULT IN TODAY'S WORLD IS SO HOT EITHER; 23. WHEREVER YOU ARE, JOSEPH WE'LL NEED MORE THAN ONE BOOK FOR YOUR WHITEWASHING; 24. THERE'S LIFE - THERE'S HOPE! HURRY!; 25. WE START OUT WONDERFULLY, BUT SOMEWHERE BEYOND THIS POINT WE STRAY; 26. THE U.S. DOLLAR YOU BOLSTER MAY BE YOUR OWN; 27. MONSOON; 28. "IF YOU ASK ME THEY SHOULD CALL IT LOONEY HOLIDAY!"; 29. HANG ON, OLD BUDDDY!; 30. DOUBLE - BARREL; 31. "I'D SAY, THAT'S PLENTY; 32. TIME OUT: SOMETHING CRUCIAL; 33. LOVE BIRDS THEY A'INT; 34. A FEW MORE WORDS FROM SINAI (Oversize 2, Folder 8)
  - #35-50 (set 2), 1966-1967; 35. PUT MORE MEANING INTO HALLOWEEN; 36. HOMEFRONT CASUALTIES; 37. A GOOD MEMORY IS GOOD FOR EVERYBODY; 38. RECESSIONAL; 39. TAXES, SPENDING CUTS VS. TAXES, SPENDING CUTS; 40. BEAUTIFUL, SWEET, GOLDEN, AUTUMN!; 41. THE OILY BIRD; 42. BET THAT'S HOW IT GOES, EVEN FOR GEORGE GALLUP; 43. OPERATION GALLUP; 44. SOME NEARBY PLANETS SAY THE NASTIEST THINGS; 45. GIANT STEP; 46. OUCH!; 47. INCONGRUOUS MEMENTOS; 48. IT'S THAT TIME AGAIN; 49. 1882 - 1965; 50. THEY CALL ME "TOPSY" (Oversize 2, Folder 9)
- Sketches
  - Rough sketches, undated; `NEVER SAW ANYTHING LIKE IT BEFORE'; WHAT CHANGES THOU HATH WROUGHT; HELP WANTED!; MR.CITIZEN; WHAT STARTED OUT TO BE A VERY DRY RUN; NEW FARM BOY; IT'S RIGHT WHERE IT HURTS!; THE OUCH DEPT.; COUNTDOWN; CROWN OF THORNS; CONSOLATION PRIZE; ACTS LIKE WHO?; SWIM SEASON RULES FOR POOR SWIMMERS; "WE HOLD THESE TRUTHS TO BE SELF EVIDENT, -THAT ALL MEN ARE CREATED EQUAL"; WHY NOT? EVERYBODY ELSE THINKS HE KNOWS!; THE SPARK; EVERY LITTLE BIT HELPS; LOST SOMEWHERE IN THE UNIVERSAL SMOG; GOSH! WE NEVER THOUGHT OF THAT; SOME WIVES WILL ARGUE ABOUT ANYTHING; BROTHER CAN YOU SPARE A TUITION FEE?; ORDERS, ORDERS, ORDERS! WHAT FO THEY THINK WE ARE, HUMAN? SANCTUARY; HOME SWEET HOME; SAD FAMILIAR WORDS AT HOME "WHEN I GROW UP, MOMMY..." THE MAN WHO CAME TO DINNER (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence, 1937; 1946-1948,; 1957-1958,; 1960,; 1964-1968,; undated (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - 1 photograph of Whitman (Mar 1966), a short biography (undated) and an assessment of the monetary value of 150 Whitman cartoons (27 Apr 1967). (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F=Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Academy Awards B2F6
Adams, Sherman B1F6
anti-missile systems B2F9
arts B1F1
auto industry B1F5
baseball B2F1
Batista, Fulgencio B1F7
Berlin B2F3
Bogart, Humphrey B2F5
brotherhood B1F5 B2F5
Brown, Pat B1F10
Bulganin, Nikolai B2F3
California B1F8 B1F10 B2F6 B2F8-B2F9
capital punishment B1F8
capitalism B1F1
cartoons B1F2
Castro, Fidel B1F7-B1F10 B2F2 B2F7
censorship B1F2
China B1F1-B1F3
civil defense B1F3
Cold War B1F6-B1F7
communism B1F2 B1F4 B2F3
Congo B1F9
Congress B1F1 B1F3 B1F10 B2F4 B2F9
Cuba B1F7-B1F9 B2F7
daylight savings time B1F6
de Gaulle, Charles B1F5
Democratic Party B1F10 B2F4
demonstrations B2F3 B2F9
disarmament B1F9
draft B2F9
drug use B2F9
economy B2F8-B2F9
education B2F8
Egypt B2F8
Eisenhower, Dwight B1F2 B1F4 B1F6-B1F10 B2F1-B2F5
elections B1F8 B2F6 B2F9
fire departments B1F5
Formosa B2F3
France B1F5 B2F1
Germany B2F3
gold prices B1F7 B2F8
Great Society B2F3
Guantanamo B1F1
guns B1F7
Hardy, Oliver B1F2
Hawaii B1F10 B2F2
Heiss, Carol B1F8
Ho Chi Minh B2F7
holidays B1F2 B1F4 B1F9 B2F2 B2F8
Hoover, J. Edgar B2F6
Israel B2F8-B2F9
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F8 B2F6-B2F9
journalism B1F6
Kaiser, Henry J. B2F9
Kennedy, John F. B1F6-B1F8 B2F8
Kennedy, Robert F. B2F6
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F4 B1F10 B2F1-B2F2
Ku Klux Klan B1F9
living conditions B2F9
Macmillan, Harold B2F2
McCarthy, Eugene B2F6
McCarthy, Joseph B2F5
Middle East B2F5
Nasser, Gamal Abdel B2F2 B2F9
Nazism B2F3 B2F9
Nehru, Jawaharlal B1F1
Nixon, Richard M. B1F2 B1F9 B2F6
nostalgia B2F7-B2F8
nuclear weapons B1F2 B1F6 B1F10 B2F2 B2F4
Olympics B1F10 B2F4 B2F6
Pacelli, Eugeneo B1F6
payola B1F9
peace B1F1 B1F3 B1F6 B1F10 B2F3-B2F5 B2F7
Pentagon B1F4
polio B2F1
politics B1F5 B1F7
pollution B2F9
population B1F10 B2F9
progress B1F2
Prohibition B2F7
prosperity B2F4
quiz shows B1F4 B1F9 B2F9
race B2F6
religion B1F3
Republican Party B1F10 B2F4 B2F8
Rockefeller, Nelson B2F6
Rockwell, George Lincoln B2F9
Russia B1F1 B1F3-B1F4 B1F7 B1F9-B1F10 B2F1 B2F3
schools B1F3 B2F4
science B1F3 B2F4 B2F7
segregation B1F9
Soviet Union B1F3 B1F5 B2F2-B2F4
space exploration B1F1-B1F4
Sputnik B1F2 B2F4
Stalin, Joseph B2F1 B2F8
Stalin, Svetlana B2F8
Stevenson, Adlai E. B2F4
strikes B2F9
Supreme Court B1F3
Syria B1F1
taxes B1F1 B2F1 B2F6 B2F8-B2F9
Taylor, Elizabeth B2F2
television B1F4 B1F9 B2F6 B2F9
Temple, Shirley B2F8
Torre, Marie B1F6
tourism B2F8
Truman, Harry S. B1F6
Twiggy B2F8
U.S. dollar B1F8
U.S. Senate B1F7
UNICEF B2F9
United Nations B1F3
University of California-Berkeley B2F3
USS Pueblo B2F7
Venezuela B1F7
Vietnam War B1F4 B2F6-B2F7
war B1F1 B2F3
water safety B2F2 B2F5
Westmoreland, William C. B2F6
women's rights B1F3